<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="poem">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Widsith</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Not Applicable</publisher>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Wikisource</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <head>Widsith</head>
      <lg>
				<l>Widsið spoke, unlocked his wordhoard,</l>
				<l>he who most of all people over the earth</l>
				<l>traveled among tribes; often in great halls he received</l>
				<l>handsome gifts. He came from the people</l>
				<l>of the Myrgings. He with Ealhhilde, </l>
				<l>the fair peace-weaver, first traveled</l>
				<l>seeking the home of the king of the Ostrogoths,</l>
				<l>Ermanric, east of the Angle's land,</l>
				<l>hostile oathbreaker. He began then to speak a great many words:</l>
				<l>"I have learned by asking many men who rule tribes!</l>
				<l>Men shall each live in good custom,</l>
				<l>a leader after others, governing their homeland,</l>
				<l>whoever desires his throne to prosper.</l>
				<l>There was Hwala, for a while the best,</l>
				<l>and Alexander (the Great) most powerful</l>
				<l>of all mankind, and he most throve</l>
				<l>Of those whom I have heard of over the earth.</l>
				<l>Atilla ruled the Huns, Ermanric the Goths,</l>
				<l>Becca the Banings, Gifica the Burgundians.</l>
				<l>Caesar ruled the Greeks and Caelic the Finns,</l>
				<l>Hagena the Rugians, and Heoden the Glomman.</l>
				<l>Witta ruled the Swaefe, Wada Haelsings,</l>
				<l>Meaca Myrgings, Mearchealf the Hundings (same as the Langobards).</l>
				<l>Theodric ruled the Franks, Thyle the Rondings,</l>
				<l>Breoca the Brondings, Billing the Werns.</l>
				<l>Oswin ruled the Eows and Fin the Jutes,</l>
				<l>Fin Folkwalding the Frisian tribes.</l>
				<l>Sighere ruled the Sea-Danes the longest,</l>
				<l>Hnaef the Hocings, Helm the Wulfings,</l>
				<l>Wald the Woings, Wod the Thuringians,</l>
				<l>Saeferth the Sycgans, Ongendtheow the Swedes,</l>
				<l>Sceafthere the Ymbran, Sheaf the Langobards,</l>
				<l>Hunn the Haetwere, and Holen the Wrosnan.</l>
				<l>Hringwald was called the Herefaren's king.</l>
				<l>Offa ruled the Angel, Alewih the Danes:</l>
				<l>He was of those men the noblest,</l>
				<l>however he did not achieve more valorous deeds than Offa,</l>
				<l>but Offa won first of men, </l>
				<l>while a youth, the greatest kingdom.</l>
				<l>Not any of his contemporaries were greater in valorous deeds</l>
				<l>at fighting. With his one sword </l>
				<l>he defined the boundary against the Myrgings</l>
				<l>by Fifeldore (the Eider estuary), held afterwards</l>
				<l>by the Angels and the Suebi as he'd won it.</l>
				<l>Hrothwulf and Hrothgar held longest </l>
				<l>kinship together, uncle and sister's son,</l>
				<l>after they drove off the Viking trible</l>
				<l>and humbled Ingeld's vanguard,</l>
				<l>and at Heorot cut to pieces the force of the Heathobards.</l>
				<l>As I traversed many foreign lands</l>
				<l>throughout a wide region, good and evil</l>
				<l>I experienced there, deprived of my people,</l>
				<l>far from generous kinsmen, and served far and wide. </l>
				<l>Therefore I will sing and speak a tale, </l>
				<l>Making known before the company in the mead-hall</l>
				<l>how the well-born would be generous with choice gifts to me.</l>
				<l>I was with the Huns and with the Ostrogoths,</l>
				<l>with the Swedes and with the Geats and with the South-Danes.</l>
				<l>With the Wenlas I was, and with the Varn, and with the Vikings.</l>
				<l>With the Gibids I was and with the Winedas and with the Gefflegans.</l>
				<l>With the Angles I was and with the Swaefe and with the Aenenas.</l>
				<l>With the Saxons I was and the Sycgans and with the Suardones.</l>
				<l>With the Hronan I was and the Deans and with the Heathoramas.</l>
				<l>With the Thuringians I was and with the Throwend </l>
				<l>and with the Burgundians; There I received a necklace;</l>
				<l>there Guthhere gave a goodly treasure </l>
				<l>to reward songs; that king was not stingy!</l>
				<l>With the Franks I was and with the Frisians and with the Framtings.</l>
				<l>With the Rugians I was and with the Glomman and with the Rome-foreigners.</l>
				<l>Likewise I was in Italy with Aelfwine</l>
				<l>who had of all mankind whom I have learned </l>
				<l>the quickest hand to earning praise, </l>
				<l>a generous heart distributing rings</l>
				<l>bright treasures, that son of Edwin!</l>
				<l>With the Sercings I was and with the Serae.</l>
				<l>With the Greeks I was and with the Finns and with Caesar,</l>
				<l>he who ruled over many towns of revelry, </l>
				<l>possessed riches and treasures and the realm of the Romans.</l>
				<l>With the Irish I was and with the Picts and with the Lapps.</l>
				<l>With the Lidwiccas I was and with the Leonas and with the Langobards,</l>
				<l>With heathens and with heroes and with the Hundings (could heathens and heroes be puns?).</l>
				<l>with the Israelites I was and with the Assyrians, </l>
				<l>with the Hebrews and with the Indus and with the Egyptians.</l>
				<l>WIth the Moids I was and with the Perse, and with the Myrgings</l>
				<l>and the Mofdings and the Ongendmyrgings</l>
				<l>and with the Amothings. With the east Thuringians I was</l>
				<l>and with the Ilwan and with the Austrogoths and Idumings. </l>
				<l>And I was with Ermanric all the time,</l>
				<l>There the king of the Goths was good and generous to me,</l>
				<l>first among the townspeople, gave me a ring</l>
				<l>in which of refined gold, the count of </l>
				<l>six hundred shillings were reckoned,</l>
				<l>Which I gave into the possession of Eadgils,</l>
				<l>my lord protector, when I came home,</l>
				<l>to my beloved lord because it was he who gave me land,</l>
				<l>the king of the Myrgings, my father's inheritance.</l>
				<l>And then to me Ealhhild gave a second ring, </l>
				<l>the queen of the army fighting men, the daughter of Edwin. </l>
				<l>Her praise stretched throughout many lands</l>
				<l>when I in song must say</l>
				<l>where under the sky I best knew</l>
				<l>the gold-adorned queen distributing gifts.</l>
				<l>Then with Scilling our clear voices</l>
				<l>we raised before our victory lord</l>
				<l>loudly with harp, singing loud to the harp</l>
				<l>then many men of proud spirits</l>
				<l>who had good knowledge spoke words</l>
				<l>that they had never heard a better song.</l>
				<l>Thence I traversed all the land of the Ostrogoths, </l>
				<l>I sought the best battle comrades</l>
				<l>that was ever the household of Ermanric.</l>
				<l>Hache I sought and Beadecan and the Herelingas</l>
				<l>Emerca I sought and Fridla and the East-goths,</l>
				<l>wise and good, father of Unwen</l>
				<l>Seccan I sought and Beccan, Seafola and Theodric</l>
				<l>Heathoric and Sifecta, Lotherus and Incgentheow.</l>
				<l>Edwin I sought and Elsa, Agelmund and Hungar,</l>
				<l>and the proud company of the Withmyrgings.</l>
				<l>Wulfhere I sought and Wyrmhere, very often warfare was not at rest</l>
				<l>when the Hraede army with hard swords</l>
				<l>around the Wistle wood must defend</l>
				<l>the ancestral lands of Attila's people.</l>
				<l>Raedhere I sought and Rondhere, Rumstan and Gislaharius,</l>
				<l>Withergield and Freotheric, Wudga and Hama</l>
				<l>there were not the worst comrades in arms</l>
				<l>Though I mention them at the last.</l>
				<l>Very often from that company flew the whining</l>
				<l>and shrieking spear against a hostile people.</l>
				<l>Wanderers there ruled with wound gold</l>
				<l>over men and women, Wudga and Hama.</l>
				<l>Thus I have always found it in journeying</l>
				<l>that they be dearest to their subjects</l>
				<l>whom God has given the right to rule men</l>
				<l>for holding while he lives here.</l>
				<l>Thus are fated to wandering and roving</l>
				<l>are the minstrel men throughout many regions,</l>
				<l>saying at need, speaking thank-words,</l>
				<l>always meeting someone south or north</l>
				<l>appreciative of poems with generous gifts for those</l>
				<l>who before military men will will heighten their reputation</l>
				<l>to do valorous deeds until everything passes,</l>
				<l>light and life together. He who works for praise </l>
				<l>has under the heavens lasting glory.</l>
			</lg>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>